So here, we call it 1,000 cities with one face. So as an architect in China, I have to ask myself, what can I do about it? One day, I was walking on a street, I saw people selling fish. And they put the fish in this cubic fish tank.
Entonces, aquí, lo llamamos 1000 ciudades con una cara. Como arquitecto en China, tengo que preguntarme, ¿qué puedo hacer al respecto? Un día, caminando por una calle vi gente vendiendo pescado. Y habían puesto los peces en esta pecera cúbica.
So I was asking the same question,
Entonces me hice la misma pregunta,
why a cubic space for fish? Do they like cubic space? (Laughter) Obviously not. So maybe the cubic space, cubic architecture, is cheaper, is easier to make. So, I did this small research, I put a camera and I tried to observe how fish behave in this cubic space. And then I found they probably weren't happy. The cubic space wasn't the perfect home for them, so I decided to design a new fish tank for them. I think it should be more organic, it should be a more fluid space inside. More complex interiors. I think they should feel happier living in this space, but I wouldn't know because they don't talk to me.
¿Por qué un espacio cúbico para peces? ¿Les gusta el espacio cúbico? (Risas) Obviamente no. Entonces, tal vez el espacio cúbico, la arquitectura cúbica, es más barata, es más fácil de hacer. Entonces, hice esta pequeña investigación, Instalé una cámara e intenté observar cómo se comportan los peces en este espacio cúbico. Y luego descubrí que probablemente no eran felices. El espacio cúbico no era el hogar perfecto para ellos, así que decidí diseñar una nueva pecera para ellos. Creo que debería ser más orgánica, Debería haber un espacio más fluido dentro. Interiores más complejos. Creo que deberían sentirse más felices viviendo en este espacio, pero no lo sabré porque no me hablan.
(Laughter) But one year after, we got this opportunity to design this real building for humans. This is actually a pair of towers
(Risas) Pero un año después tuvimos la oportunidad de diseñar este edificio real para humanos. Estas son en realidad un par de torres
that we built in Mississauga, a city outside Toronto. And people call this Marilyn Monroe Towers -- (Laughter) because of its curvature. And the idea was to build a tower, high-rise, residential tower, but not a box. It's more inspired by nature, with the sunshine and wind dynamics. After we finished designing the first tower,
que construimos en Mississauga, una ciudad a las afueras de Toronto. La gente las llama las Torres Marilyn Monroe, (Risas) por sus curvas. Y la idea era construir una torre, Una torre residencial de gran altura, pero no una caja. Está más inspirado por la naturaleza, con la dinámica del sol y el viento. Después de terminar de diseñar la primera torre,
they told us, you know, "You don't have to design the second one, you just repeat the same design,
nos dijeron, "No tienes que diseñar la segunda, solo repite el mismo diseño
and we pay you twice." But I said, "You cannot have two Marilyn Monroes standing there." And nature never repeats itself, so now we have two buildings that can dance together. So I have this question for myself. You know, why, in the modern city, we often think architecture is a machine, is a box? So here, I want to see how people looked at nature in the past. By looking into this Chinese traditional painting, I found that they often mixed the nature and the artificial, man-made, in a very dramatic way, so they create this emotional scenery. So in the modern city, my question is: Is there a way that we don't separate buildings and nature, but combine them? So there's another project that we built in China. It's a quite large residential complex. And it's located in a very beautiful nature setting. To be honest, the first time when I visited the site, it was too beautiful. And I almost decided to reject the project because you feel as a criminal to do anything there. I don't want to become a criminal. But my second thought was, if I didn't do it, they would just put, you know, standard urban towers there, anyway. And that would be a pity. So I decided I had to give it a try. So the way we did that was we took the contour lines from the existing mountains, and we took those lines and then translated them into a building. So those towers are actually taking the shapes and geometries from the nature. So each building has a different shape, a different size, different height.
y te pagamos el doble". Pero dije: "No se pueden tener dos Marilyn Monroes de pie allí". Y la naturaleza nunca se repite, Así que ahora tenemos dos edificios que pueden bailar juntos. Me tengo que hacer una pregunta. Ya saben, ¿por qué, en la ciudad moderna, a menudo pensamos que la arquitectura es una máquina, es una caja? Aquí quiero ver cómo la gente miraba la naturaleza en el pasado. Al mirar esta pintura tradicional china, descubrí que a menudo se mezclaban la naturaleza y lo artificial, hecho por el hombre, de manera dramática, y crean este escenario emocional. Entonces, en la ciudad moderna, mi pregunta es: ¿Hay alguna manera de no separar edificios y naturaleza, sino de combinarlos? Hay otro proyecto que construimos en China. Es un complejo residencial bastante grande. Y se encuentra en un entorno natural muy hermoso. Para ser sincero, la primera vez que visité el sitio, me resultó tan hermoso que casi decidí rechazar el proyecto porque me sentía como un criminal haciendo algo allí. No quiero convertirme en un criminal. Pero mi segundo pensamiento fue: si no lo hiciera ellos simplemente pondrían igualmente, allí torres urbanas estándar. Y eso sería una pena. Así que decidí que tenía que intentarlo. Así que la forma en que lo hicimos fue tomar las curvas de nivel de las montañas existentes, y esas líneas luego las tradujimos a un edificio. Esas torres están tomando formas y geometrías de la naturaleza. Cada edificio tiene una forma diferente, un tamaño diferente, diferente altura.
And they become the extension of the nature [where] they're situated. And you know, people think we use computer sometimes to design this kind of architecture, but I actually use a lot of hand sketch, because I like the randomness in the hand sketch. And they can carry sort of emotions that cannot be made by computers. Architecture and humans and nature can coexist together and are having a good relationship in this photo. Actually this guy in the photo is one of the architects on our team. I think he's been enjoying the beautiful nature scenery, and feeling relieved that he is not part of the criminals -- (Laughter) in the end. Back to the city, in Beijing, we were asked to design these urban towers. And I made this model. It's an architecture model, looks like a minimountain and minivalleys. I put this model on my table, and I watered it every day. And years later, we completed this building. And you can see how my hand sketch is being translated into the real building. And they look quite similar. It looks like a black mountain. And this is how this building is situated in the city. It's on the edge of this beautiful park. It's different, very different from the surrounding buildings, because other buildings are trying to build a wall around the nature. But what we're trying to do here is to make the building itself as a part of nature, so we can extend the nature from the park into the city. So that was the idea. A Chinese art critic drew this painting. He put our building in this painting. Can you see there's a black, tiny mountain? That looks very fit into this painting. However, in this reality, our design was being challenged that it looks so different from the surroundings. And they asked me to modify my design, either color or shape, to make the building fit the context better. So my question was, why it fits this traditional, you know, natural context, better than the reality? Maybe there's something wrong with the reality. Something wrong with the context. In the very northern part of China, we also built this opera house. It's an opera house next to the river, in the wetland park. So we decided to make this building part of the surrounding landscape and merge into the horizon. The building literally looks like a snow mountain. And people can walk on the building. During the day or when there's no opera, people come here, they can enjoy the views, and they can continue their journey from the park onto the building. When they reach the rooftop, there's an amphitheater that's framing the sky, where they can sing to the sky. Inside the opera, we have this lobby with a lot of natural light, and they can also enjoy this semi-indoor-outdoor space, and they can see the beautiful view around them. I've been building several mountains,
Y se convierten en extensión de la naturaleza donde están situados. Y saben, la gente piensa que usamos la computadora a veces para diseñar este tipo de arquitectura, pero en realidad hago muchos bocetos a mano, porque me gusta la aleatoriedad en el boceto a mano. Y pueden llevar emociones y eso no puede hacerse con computadoras. Arquitectura, humanos y naturaleza pueden coexistir juntos y están teniendo una buena relación en esta foto. En realidad, este chico de la foto es uno de los arquitectos de nuestro equipo. Creo que ha estado disfrutando del hermoso paisaje natural, y sintiéndose aliviado de que él no es parte de los criminales... (Risas) al final. De vuelta a la ciudad, en Beijing, nos pidieron diseñar unas torres urbanas. E hice este modelo. Es un modelo de arquitectura, parece una minimontaña y minivalles. Puse este modelo en mi mesa y lo regué todos los días. Y años después, completamos este edificio. Y pueden ver cómo mi dibujo a mano es traducido al edificio real. Se parecen bastante. Parece una montaña negra. Así es como este edificio está situado en la ciudad. Está al borde de este hermoso parque. Es diferente, muy diferente de los edificios circundantes, porque otros edificios tratan de construir un muro alrededor de la naturaleza. Pero lo que intentamos hacer aquí es que el edificio sea parte de la naturaleza, para que podamos extender la naturaleza del parque a la ciudad. Esa fue la idea. Un crítico de arte chino dibujó esta pintura. Puso nuestro edificio en esta pintura. ¿Pueden ver que hay una pequeña montaña negra? Se ve muy bien en esta pintura. Sin embargo, en esta realidad, nuestro diseño estaba siendo desafiado por verse tan diferente a los de los alrededores. Me pidieron que modificara mi diseño, ya sea color o forma, para hacer que el edificio se ajustara mejor al contexto. Entonces mi pregunta fue: ¿por qué se ajusta a este contexto natural tradicional, mejor que la realidad? Tal vez hay algo equivocado con la realidad. Algo está mal con el contexto. En la parte más al norte de China, también construimos esta casa de ópera. Es una casa de ópera al lado del río, en el parque de humedales. Decidimos hacer de este edificio parte del paisaje circundante y que se fundiera en el horizonte. El edificio literalmente parece una montaña nevada. La gente puede caminar sobre el edificio. Durante el día o cuando no hay ópera, la gente viene aquí, pueden disfrutar de las vistas, y pueden continuar su viaje del parque a dentro del edificio. Cuando llegan a la azotea, hay un anfiteatro que enmarca el cielo donde pueden cantar al cielo. Dentro de la ópera tenemos este lobby con mucha luz natural, y también pueden disfrutar de este espacio semi-interior-exterior, y pueden ver la hermosa vista a su alrededor. He estado construyendo varias montañas
and here I'm trying to show you
y aquí estoy tratando de mostrar
one building that I think looks like a cloud. It's the Lucas Museum of Narrative Arts that's being constructed in the city of Los Angeles. It's a museum created by George Lucas, the creator of the "Star Wars" movies. Why a building that looks like a cloud? Because I think, I imagine, the cloud is mysterious. It's nature. It's surreal when this natural element landed in the city. And it makes you feel curious about it, and you want to explore it. So that's how the building landed on earth. By lifting this museum, making it float above the ground, we can free up a lot of landscape and space underneath the building. And then we can, at the same time, create this roof garden above the building where you can visit and enjoy the view. This museum will be completed in the year 2022, and you're all invited when it's completed. So after building all these mountains and clouds, now we're building these volcanoes back in China. This is actually a huge sports park with four stadiums in it, with one football stadium [with] 40,000 seats in there. So it's a very large project. And you see from this photo, you can hardly tell where there's building and where there's landscape. So the building becomes a landscape. Even becomes a land art, where people can walk around the building, they can climb this building as they're wandering in this volcano park. And this rendering shows one of the spaces in those volcanoes. This is actually a swimming pool with natural light coming from above. So, what we're trying to create actually is an environment that blurs the boundary in between architecture and nature. So architecture is no longer a functional machine for living.
un edificio que creo que parece una nube. Es el Museo Lucas de Artes Narrativas que se está construyendo en la ciudad de Los Ángeles. Es un museo creado por George Lucas, el creador de las películas de "Star Wars". ¿Por qué un edificio que se parece a una nube? Porque creo, imagino, la nube es misteriosa. Es la naturaleza. Es surrealista cuando este elemento natural aterrizó en la ciudad. Y te hace sentir curiosidad al respecto, y quieres explorarlo Así es como el edificio aterrizó en la tierra. Al levantar este museo, haciéndolo flotar sobre el suelo Podemos liberar mucho paisaje y espacio debajo del edificio. Y luego podemos, al mismo tiempo, crear este jardín en la azotea sobre el edificio que pueden visitar y disfrutar de la vista. Este museo se completará en el año 2022, y todos están invitados cuando se complete. Después de construir todas estas montañas y nubes, ahora estamos construyendo estos volcanes de vuelta en China. Este es en realidad un gran parque deportivo con cuatro estadios adentro, con un estadio de fútbol con 40 000 asientos. Es un proyecto muy grande. Y ven en esta foto que difícilmente se puede saber dónde hay construcción y dónde hay paisaje. El edificio se convierte en un paisaje. Incluso se convierte en un "land art", donde la gente puede caminar alrededor del edificio, puede subir a este edificio mientras deambulan en este parque de volcanes. Esta representación muestra uno de los espacios en esos volcanes. Esto es en realidad una piscina con luz natural que viene de arriba. Entonces, lo que estamos tratando de crear en realidad es un entorno que desdibuja el límite entre arquitectura y naturaleza. Así la arquitectura ya no es una máquina funcional para vivir.
It also reflects the nature around us. It also reflects our soul and spirit. So, as an architect, I don't think in the future we should repeat those soulless matchboxes anymore. I think what I'm looking for is the opportunity to create a future with harmony in between humans and nature. Thank you very much. (Applause)
También refleja la naturaleza que nos rodea. También refleja nuestra alma y espíritu. Como arquitecto, no creo que en el futuro deberíamos repetir esas cajas de fósforos sin alma nunca más. Creo que lo que busco es la oportunidad para crear un futuro con armonía entre humanos y naturaleza. Muchas gracias. (Aplausos)